Guide to the Chet Huntley Papers 1912-2017
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana-Missoula
Chet Huntley Papers
circa 1912-2017
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana--Missoula Missoula, Montana 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 078
Huntley, Chet (Chester Robert), 1911-1974
18.0 linear feet and 2 bronze statues
Chet Huntley was a nationally-known television and radio reporter from Montana. This collection includes an array of materials by and about Huntley: biographical information, personal and professional correspondence; scripts written for his radio and television projects, speaking engagements, and news commentary projects; press clippings, primarily spanning his years with NBC; obituaries published in diverse outlets; an extensive photographic collection; a small sampling of news and documentary broadcasts; and some three-dimensional memorabilia. The collection also includes extensive information regarding Huntley's role with the development of Big Sky Resort in Montana.
Biographical Note
Chester Robert Huntley was born in Cardwell, Montana, on December 10, 1911. His parents, Percy "Pat" and Blanche Huntley, claimed a homestead on 960 acres of land near Saco in northern Montana. Percy Huntley was a former railroad telegrapher and Blanche was a schoolteacher. The Huntleys built a one-room schoolhouse on their land so Chet could stay close to home and help work the farm. The early 1920s was a very difficult period for wheat farmers in eastern Montana and Percy returned to a telegraphy position with the Great Northern Railroad. The Huntleys sold their Saco homestead in 1924 and the family moved frequently around southern Montana until 1926. In that year they settled in Whitehall, Montana, where Chet graduated from high school in 1929. Although he began his education at Montana State College in Bozeman with plans to become a physician, Huntley left that school in 1932 when he won a scholarship to study oratory at the Cornish School of Arts in Seattle. The experience altered his career plans, and he graduated from the University of Washington in 1934 with a degree in speech and drama.
During his senior year in Seattle, Huntley began working at radio station KPCB where his duties included advertising sales, news writing, and announcing. This job soon led to reporting positions at other radio stations: KHO in Spokane, Washington; KGW in Portland, Oregon; and KFI in Los Angeles. In 1939 Huntley joined the staff of KNX, the CBS Radio affiliate in Los Angeles. At KNX he began writing and producing short news commentary programs. Huntley continued to pursue news commentary projects under various titles throughout his broadcasting career. From 1951 to 1955 he worked for ABC Radio and Television in Los Angeles. Early in 1955, he was hired by the NBC Pacific Division to work as West Coast commentator and reporter for the Today show. In June 1955, NBC transferred him to their New York headquarters with the promise of a major news program.
His first major national assignment came in 1956 when he covered the Republican and Democratic national conventions with David Brinkley. The pairing drew the highest ratings among the three national networks for convention coverage. In October NBC chose the two men to co-anchor the network's fifteen-minute weekday evening news program. The program had an innovative format with Huntley reporting from New York and Brinkley from Washington DC. In 1963 the Huntley-Brinkley Report became one of the first thirty-minute network news programs. During its fourteen-year tenure the Huntley-Brinkley Report was one of the most professionally recognized and highly rated news programs on television, eventually winning seven Emmy and two Peabody awards. Both Brinkley and Huntley received numerous individual broadcasting awards. Huntley was also involved with several other news programs at NBC. During the late 1950s and early 1960s, he edited and narrated a series of Sunday evening news broadcasts. Variously titled Outlook, NBC Kaleidoscope, and Chet Huntley Reporting, the program presented expanded commentary on various news events and issues. Through most of the 1960s he also wrote and narrated a five-minute NBC radio program of editorial commentary titled Chet Huntley's Perspective on the News, with a weekend equivalent named Emphasis: Plain Talk.
Throughout his career Huntley caused controversy by blurring the lines between news reporting and political commentary. He was a vocal critic of Senator Joseph McCarthy and entertainment industry anti-communism activists. His commentary programs spoke out against internment of Japanese-Americans during World War II, advocated school integration in Little Rock, Arkansas, and critiqued the presidency of Richard M. Nixon. Huntley defended his commentary programs by declaring that he never allowed his opinions to influence newscasts; however, one industry critic accused him of editorializing with his eyebrows during the Huntley-Brinkley Report. Huntley precipitated other controversies. As the owner of a Montana cattle ranch, Huntley recorded commercials and accepted speaking engagements to promote the beef industry. These activities generated profuse criticism from other professionals concerned about maintaining the image of broadcasting objectivity and integrity. He caused a rift with David Brinkley in 1967 when Huntley crossed an American Federation of Television and Radio Artists' picket line claiming that news anchors did not belong in the same union as "actors, singers, and dancers."
During the height of his NBC broadcasting career Huntley wrote a memoir of his Montana youth. Random House published The Generous Years: Remembrances of a Frontier Boyhood in 1968. He retired from NBC on July 31, 1970. For the final broadcast of the Huntley-Brinkley Report, Huntley initiated the team's signature closing with the words "Good night, David." However, Brinkley altered form with his response "Good-bye, Chet." Before signing off Huntley addressed a final statement to the television audience, "Be patient and have courage, there will be better and happier news some day, if we work at it."
Huntley met his first wife, Ingrid Eleanor Rolin, while living in Seattle. They were married in 1936, had two daughters, and divorced in 1959. Huntley met his second wife, Lewis Tipton "Tippy" Stringer, in 1959. Tippy was a weather announcer for the DC NBC affiliate. They had no children. Huntley stayed active in retirement, broadcasting commentaries, recording commercials for American Airlines, and contracting with the airline to sponsor a new PBS program The American Experience, a series for which Huntley frequently narrated.
Big Sky, Montana, was Huntley's biggest post-retirement project, both in terms of personal investment and financial scale. The project started as a 15,000-acre resort in the Gallatin Valley of south central Montana that eventually became a permanent community. The primary corporation directing Big Sky development was Chrysler Realty, a conglomeration co-funded by Chrysler Motor Corporation, Conoco Oil, Burlington Northern Railroad, Montana Power Co. and Northwest Airlines. The project included one of the first privately owned ski resorts in the United States. Huntley died of cancer March 20, 1974, in Bozeman, Montana, three days before the opening ceremonies for Big Sky.
This collection includes an array of materials by and about Huntley: biographical information, personal and professional correspondence; scripts written for his radio and television projects, speaking engagements, and news commentary projects; press clippings, primarily spanning his years with NBC; obituaries published in diverse outlets; an extensive photographic collection; a small sampling of news and documentary broadcasts; and some three-dimensional memorabilia. The collection also includes extensive information regarding Huntley's role with the Big Sky Resort. Writings include several articles Huntley wrote for magazines and essay collections as well as extensive materials relating to The Generous Years, an autobiographical account of his Montana childhood. Subject files reflect Huntley's varied research interests and clipping files consist of newspaper and magazine articles about Huntley, published through out his professional career and after his death. Big Sky materials include written proposals, correspondence with potential investors, development blue prints, promotional materials, and press clippings. Audio-visual materials include an extensive photographic collection, a small sampling of news and documentary broadcasts, and a few audiotape recordings. Mounted artifacts range from bronze sculptures to framed awards, from appreciation plaques and medals to oversize certificates.
The collection is divided into thirteen series:
Series I: Biographical, 0.25 linear feet and partial oversize box, 1928-1975
Series II: General Correspondence, 0.25 linear feet, 1928-1977
Series III: Radio and TV Scripts, 2.5 linear feet, 1942-1974
Series IV: Speeches, 0.5 linear feet, 1964-1973
Series V: Writings, 1.0 linear feet, 1965-1973
Series VI: Subject, 0.5 linear feet and partial oversize box, 1964-1973
Series VII: Clippings, 1.0 linear feet and partial oversize box, 1957-1974
Series VIII: Big Sky Resort, 0.5 linear feet and partial oversize box, 1965-1975
Series IX: Photographs, 2.0 linear feet and one oversize box, circa1920-1974
Series X: Audio and Moving Images, 1.0 linear feet, 1963-1974
Series XI: Awards, Memorials, and Memorabilia, 6.0 linear feet 1954-1974
Series XII: Artwork, 2 items, 1972
Series XIII: Accession 2019-003, 2.5 linear feet, 1912-2017
Film reels 78(X):10, 78(X):12, and 78(X):13 were transferred to VHS video during original processing. The VHS tape is designated as 78(X):18.
Audio reel 78(X):7 was transferred to cassette tape at an unknown time. This cassette is designated as 78(X):19.
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana-Missoula.
Portions of this collection, mostly television/radio transcripts, were housed in the radio-television collections at Montana State University-Bozeman and the Museum of the Rockies in Bozeman prior to accession into the K. Ross Toole Archives collections.
The majority of the collection was received from Tippy Huntley in 1979. Additional materials were received from the Museum of the Rockies, 1980; Callie Allison, 1980; and the Special Collections department at Montana State University, 1999. The Chrysler Realty Corporation donated the two bronze sculptures in 1980. In 2018 Huntley's daughter, Sharon Huntley Kahn, donated additional materials which are considered Accession 2019-003. Series XIII comprises the majority of this donation.
The State Historical Society of Wisconsin holds a significant collection of Chet Huntley papers in its Mass Communication History Center, and there are also Huntley materials in the records of the National Broadcasting Company, Inc.
The John F. Kennedy Library holds a small collection of Chet Huntley papers exclusively regarding reports and commentary following the assassination of President Kennedy.
The Montana Historical Society holds some radio recordings of Huntley in its general Montana History Collections.
The Museum of the Rockies holds some artifacts, including an Emmy award and Huntley's typewriter.
Radio journalists -- United States; Television journalists--United States
Personal papers--United States; Scripts; Speeches, addresses, etc., American; Photographs; Sound recordings; Moving images; Artifacts
Montana; Artifacts; Moving Images; Photographs; Sound Recordings; Journalism; Literature
Radio journalism--United States; Resorts--Montana; Television broadcasting of news--United States
Huntley, Chet, 1911-1974. The generous years
Big Sky of Montana, Inc.; NBC News
- Biographical, 1925-1975; Series I; 0.25 linear feet and partial oversize box
  This series includes an array of personal and biographical materials regarding Chet Huntley. Materials include memorabilia from Huntley's various endeavors, items he collected that reflect on his family history, and general biographical documents. Elementary and high school materials include a report card from 1925 and yearbooks ("The Trail") from 1927 and 1929. White House documents in this series consist of two photocopied Nixon Administration staff memos critiquing Huntley's public comments on Administration policies as well as proposing intervention on behalf of the Big Sky Resort development if Huntley would agree to support Montana Republican candidates.
  - Biographical, 1928-1975 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Elementary and high school materials, 1925-1929 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - 'Huntley Family Tree' compiled and written by P.A. Huntley, undated (Box-folder 1/3)
  - University of Washington B.A. Degree, 1942 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Press cards NBC, travel documents, 1959-1969 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Passports, 1959-1969 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Biography from NBC; Huntley, Paxton, Kiker, 1968 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Bicentennial Council Appointment, 1973 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Clippings, Saco School, undated (Box-folder 1/9)
  - NBC Magazine 1962-1963 Edition "Chet Huntley Reporting" (Box-folder 1/10)
  - NBC Star Album 1964-1965, Souvenir Guide to Television's Finest Schedule of Entertainment, News, Information and Sports (Box-folder 1/11)
  - Presidential election returns chart with message from Chet Huntley, 1968 (Box-folder 1/12)
  - White House documents regarding Huntley, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 1/13)
  - "Crisis, Conflict and Change in TV News," Look, November 7, 1961 (Box-folder 22OS/1)
  - "The Huntley-Brinkley Bandwagon," Electronic Age, Summer, 1970 (Box-folder 22OS/2)
  - Article in America, (a publication in Russian, published by USIA), 1967 (Box-folder 22OS/3)
- General Correspondence, 1928-1977; Series II; 0.25 linear feet
  This series includes incoming and outgoing correspondence with a diverse group of public figures and personal friends. Correspondence regarding Huntley's writing projects (series V) and the Big Sky Resort (series VIII) are located within those series. Materials include correspondence with international, national, and state political leaders, famous journalists and entertainers, well-regarded authors, and other American cultural figures. Some of the most notable individuals in this series are Chung Yum Kim (South Korea), Lyndon B. Johnson, Richard Nixon, Gerald Ford, Hubert H. Humphrey, Mike Mansfield, Arnold Olsen, Ted Kennedy, Barry Goldwater, Nelson Rockefeller, Henry M. Jackson, Dean Rusk, George C. Wallace, Tim Babcock, H.G. Merriam, John Chancellor, Vadim Golovanov, Bob Hope, Joan Crawford, Eleanor Roosevelt, Mitzi Gaynor, Jack Benny, Douglas Fairbanks, Dick Cavett, A. B. Guthrie, Jr., Lady Bird Johnson, and Mrs. Chester W. Nimitz.
  - 1928-1969 (Box-folder 1/14)
  - 1970-1973 (Box-folder 1/15)
  - 1974 (Box-folder 1/16)
  - 1975-1977 (Box-folder 1/17)
  - White House Invitations, 1961-1966 (Box-folder 1/18)
- Radio and TV Scripts, 1942-1974; Series III; 2.5 linear feet
  This series includes transcripts from Huntley's radio and television programs. Materials are predominantly narrator copy for news broadcasts but a few interview transcriptions are also present. The contents within this series are arranged conceptually and chronologically. Box one contains general materials from both radio and television broadcasts. Often a definite determination of radio or television broadcast could not be established; thus, materials are arranged chronologically based on the best available date information. Box one also includes a script for "Strange and Terrible Times." The film version of this production, 78(X):15, can be found in the Audio and Moving Pictures series of this collection. Boxes two through six are all radio scripts. Perspective, Emphasis, and Horizons were five-minute editorial commentaries for NBC Radio.
  - "A Word for the War", 1942-12-06 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Evening Broadcast, 1947-12-23 (Box-folder 2/2)
  - Evening Broadcast, 1947-12-24 (Box-folder 2/3)
  - First Trans-Atlantic Television Broadcast, 1962-07-23 (Box-folder 2/4)
  - "Seventy Hours and Thirty Minutes" Kennedy Assassination, 1963-11 (Box-folder 2/5)
  - Commentary on Hatred, 1963-11-22 (Box-folder 2/6)
  - "Vietnam; War of the Ballot", 1966-09-11 (Box-folder 2/7)
  - Second Sunday: Year 2000, 1966-12-11 (Box-folder 2/8)
  - Will and Ariel Durant Interview, 1967-01 (Box-folder 2/9)
  - Floyd McKissick Interview, 1967-01 (Box-folder 2/10)
  - Astronaut Eulogy, 1967-02-01 (Box-folder 2/11)
  - Matter of Life, 1967-03-08 (Box-folder 2/12)
  - "The Abundant Land", 1967-08-25 (Box-folder 2/13)
  - Commentary on the King Assassination, 1968-04-04 (Box-folder 2/14)
  - Home Country USA, 1968-04-05 (Box-folder 2/15)
  - Monitor, 1968-11 (Box-folder 2/16)
  - Commentary on Lyndon Johnson, 1969-01-14 (Box-folder 2/17)
  - Monitor, 1969-04 (Box-folder 2/18)
  - Script for Guideline, 1969-08-17 (Box-folder 2/19)
  - Script for David Frost Show, 1969-09-08 (Box-folder 2/20)
  - Last Huntley-Brinkley Report, 1970-07-31 (Box-folder 2/21)
  - Script for the American Experience Film "The Fabulous Country", 1972 (Box-folder 2/22)
  - Script for the American Experience Film "Strange and terrible Times", undated (Box-folder 2/23)
  - Commentary on Northern Ireland, undated (Box-folder 2/24)
  - Gromyko Interview, undated (Box-folder 2/25)
  - "Yours is the Earth" KGW-TV, undated (Box-folder 2/26)
  - George Polk Memorial Awards, undated (Box-folder 2/27)
  - Family Circle, undated (Box-folder 2/28)
  - Script order forms, undated (Box-folder 2/29)
  - Scripts, Unknown Titles, undated (Box-folder 2/30)
  - Scripts, No Titles, 1951-1969 (Box-folder 2/31)
  - Perspective, November-December 1968 (Box-folder 3/1)
  - Perspective, January 1969 (Box-folder 3/2)
  - Perspective, February 1969 (Box-folder 3/3)
  - Perspective, March 1969 (Box-folder 3/4)
  - Perspective, April 1969 (Box-folder 3/5)
  - Perspective, May 1969 (Box-folder 3/6)
  - Perspective, June 1969 (Box-folder 3/7)
  - Perspective, July 1969 (Box-folder 3/8)
  - Perspective, August 1969 (Box-folder 3/9)
  - Perspective, September 1969 (Box-folder 3/10)
  - Perspective, October 1969 (Box-folder 3/11)
  - Perspective, November 1969 (Box-folder 3/12)
  - Perspective, December 1969 (Box-folder 3/13)
  - Perspective, January 1970 (Box-folder 3/14)
  - Perspective, February 1970 (Box-folder 3/15)
  - Perspective, March 1970 (Box-folder 3/16)
  - Perspective, April 1970 (Box-folder 3/17)
  - Perspective, May 1970 (Box-folder 3/18)
  - Perspective, June-July 1970 (Box-folder 3/19)
  - Emphasis, June 1966 (Box-folder 3/20)
  - Emphasis, September 1968 (Box-folder 4/1)
  - Emphasis, October 1968 (Box-folder 4/2)
  - Emphasis, November 1968 (Box-folder 4/3)
  - Emphasis, December 1968 (Box-folder 4/4)
  - Emphasis, January 1969 (Box-folder 4/5)
  - Emphasis, February 1969 (Box-folder 4/6)
  - Emphasis, March 1969 (Box-folder 4/7)
  - Emphasis, April 1969 (Box-folder 4/8)
  - Emphasis, May 1969 (Box-folder 4/9)
  - Emphasis, June 1969 (Box-folder 4/10)
  - Emphasis, July 1969 (Box-folder 4/11)
  - Emphasis, August 1969 (Box-folder 4/12)
  - Emphasis, September 1969 (Box-folder 4/13)
  - Emphasis, October 1969 (Box-folder 4/14)
  - Emphasis, November 1969 (Box-folder 4/15)
  - Emphasis, December 1969 (Box-folder 4/16)
  - Emphasis, January 1970 (Box-folder 4/17)
  - Emphasis, February 1970 (Box-folder 4/18)
  - Emphasis, March 1970 (Box-folder 4/19)
  - Emphasis, April 1970 (Box-folder 4/20)
  - Emphasis, May 1970 (Box-folder 4/21)
  - Horizons, September 1970 (Box-folder 5/1)
  - Horizons, October 1970 (Box-folder 5/2)
  - Horizons, November 1970 (Box-folder 5/3)
  - Horizons, December 1970 (Box-folder 5/4)
  - Horizons, January 1971 (Box-folder 5/5)
  - Horizons, February 1971 (Box-folder 5/6)
  - Horizons, March 1971 (Box-folder 5/7)
  - Horizons, April 1971 (Box-folder 5/8)
  - Horizons, May 1971 (Box-folder 5/9)
  - Horizons, June 1971 (Box-folder 5/10)
  - Horizons, July 1971 (Box-folder 5/11)
  - Horizons, August 1971 (Box-folder 5/12)
  - Horizons, September 1971 (Box-folder 5/13)
  - Horizons, October 1971 (Box-folder 5/14)
  - Horizons, November 1971 (Box-folder 5/15)
  - Horizons, December 1971 (Box-folder 5/16)
  - Radio Broadcasts, January 1972 (Box-folder 5/17)
  - Radio Broadcasts, February 1972 (Box-folder 5/18)
  - Radio Broadcasts, March 1972 (Box-folder 5/19)
  - Radio Broadcasts, April 1972 (Box-folder 6/1)
  - Radio Broadcasts, May 1972 (Box-folder 6/2)
  - Radio Broadcasts, June 1972 (Box-folder 6/3)
  - Radio Broadcasts, July 1972 (Box-folder 6/4)
  - Radio Broadcasts, August 1972 (Box-folder 6/5)
  - Radio Broadcasts, September 1972 (Box-folder 6/6)
  - Radio Broadcasts, October 1972 (Box-folder 6/7)
  - Radio Broadcasts, November 1972 (Box-folder 6/8)
  - Radio Broadcasts, December 1972 (Box-folder 6/9)
  - Radio Broadcasts, January 1973 (Box-folder 6/10)
  - Radio Broadcasts, February 1973 (Box-folder 6/11)
  - Radio Broadcasts, March 1973 (Box-folder 6/12)
  - Radio Broadcasts, April 1973 (Box-folder 6/13)
  - Radio Broadcasts, May 1973 (Box-folder 6/14)
  - Radio Broadcasts, June 1973 (Box-folder 6/15)
  - Radio Broadcasts, July 1973 (Box-folder 7/1)
  - Radio Broadcasts, August 1973 (Box-folder 7/2)
  - Radio Broadcasts, September 1973 (Box-folder 7/3)
  - Radio Broadcasts, October 1973 (Box-folder 7/4)
  - Radio Broadcasts, November 1973 (Box-folder 7/5)
  - Radio Broadcasts, December 1973 (Box-folder 7/6)
  - Radio Broadcasts, January 1974 (Box-folder 7/7)
  - Radio Broadcasts, February-March 1974 (Box-folder 7/8)
- Speeches, 1964-1973; Series IV; 0.5 linear feet
  This series contains a mixture of typed and handwritten text for speeches Huntley delivered during his career as a newscaster and after retirement. Most documents exhibit editorial changes Huntley inserted up to the moment before delivering the address. Dates are identified in the content description whenever a date could be reliably established. Materials reflect a range of topics from commentary on current events to advocacy for investment proposals.
  - Montana Centennial Dinner, Washington D.C., April 17, 1964 (Box-folder 8/1)
  - New Jersey education Association, November 4, 1966 (Box-folder 8/2)
  - Acceptance Speech; Distinguished Service Award of 1967, National Association of Broadcasters, Chicago, April 4, 1967 (Box-folder 8/3)
  - Constitutional Rights Foundation, Los Angeles CA, May 13, 1967 (Box-folder 8/4)
  - Rochester Institute of Technology, June 3, 1967 (Box-folder 8/5)
  - General Foods National Financial Conference, 1968 (Box-folder 8/6)
  - "What Do We Say" The Governors Conference on Aging, May 3, 1968 (Box-folder 8/7)
  - Dedication of J.E. Corette Steam Electric Plant, Billings, September 22, 1968 (Box-folder 8/8)
  - Peace Luncheon, March 1968 (Box-folder 8/9)
  - Ninth Annual George Washington Awards Dinner, April 16, 1969 (Box-folder 8/10)
  - Dinner at the Cartwheel inn, Bozeman, March 2, 1972 (Box-folder 8/11)
  - American Hotel and Motel association, 61st annual Convention, Phoenix AZ, December 7, 1972 (Box-folder 8/12)
  - Brand Names Foundation Dinner Pamphlet, 1973 (Box-folder 8/13)
  - NSBA Convention, April 7, 1973 (Box-folder 8/14)
  - FSBA Dinner, May 22, 1973 (Box-folder 8/15)
  - National Forum on Growth with Environmental Quality, September 26, 1973 (Box-folder 8/16)
  - American Airlines, undated (Box-folder 8/17)
  - Journalism (two drafts), undated (Box-folder 8/18)
  - Discover America Travel Organization Convention, undated (Box-folder 8/19)